Guide to the Westinghouse Electric and Manufacturing Company, Pittsburgh, Pa., Contracts Collection 1892-1901 AIS.1963.24
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Westinghouse Electric and Manufacturing Company, Pittsburgh, Pa., Contracts Collection
1895-1901
ULS Archives & Special Collections
AIS.1963.24
5.63 Linear Feet (9 boxes)
Business records of Westinghouse Electric Manufacturing Company, East Pittsburgh, Pa., 1892-1901. Collection documents acquisitions of machinery and technology such as cranes, presses, drills, and pumps. Records include blueprints, photographs, carbon copies of telegrams, signed forms, memorandums, and correspondence.
History
Industrialist and inventor of the compressed air brake George Westinghouse incorporated the Westinghouse Electric Manufacturing Company in 1891. With its giant factory located in East Pittsburgh, Pa., the Westinghouse Electric Manufacturing Company soon became the Edison General Electric Company's main rival in the contest to provide electricity to the United States. While Edison General Electric pioneered the generation and distribution of direct current (DC) electricity, Westinghouse put all of its efforts into the development of alternating current (AC) systems. AC systems were capable of transmitting significantly more electricity from more distant sites, thus enabling the supply of power to rural areas or smaller urban centers. Westinghouse supported the research of the great Serbian inventor Nikola Tesla, and purchased patent rights to his revolutionary polyphase AC system. Edison General Electric launched a high-profile public relations campaign against the "danger" of AC systems, but scientific and commercial reason was on the side of Westinghouse. The next decade witnessed the wide adoption of AC systems around the country and overseas, with Westinghouse and Edison GE competing for markets in electrical goods, generators, turbines, and delivery systems.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection consists of records relating to the purchase of goods by the Westinghouse Electric and Manufacturing Company during the years 1892-1901. Outlays of this kind are called "capital expenditures" and differ from overhead or operating costs. Capital expenditures are investments made in technology, which continue to produce profit once it has been obtained, unlike raw materials, which are used and incorporated into products. These records therefore document activities undertaken at the highest level of management. Records include typed memoranda, handwritten notes, carbon copies of telegrams, blueprints and photographs of machinery, and signed forms. Items procured include cranes, lathes, drills, engines, pumps, and presses. Records relating to a single purchase were bound together in heavy paper sleeves. Each sleeve records contract and order number, date, title of company, and item(s) ordered. Most frequently, the final document in each sleeve is a letter granting permission to the company purchasing agent to procure the stated items at a given price. This form letter is usually signed by the second vice president, the superintendent of works, and the assistant superintendent. The collection has been arranged in a single series, ordered alphabetically by company. For multiple contracts with the same company, records are ordered chronologically.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquistion Information
Gift of Joseph A. Miller, 1963.
Previous Citation
Westinghouse Electric and Manufacturing Company, Pittsburgh, Pa. Contracts Collection, 1892-1901, AIS.1963.24, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Westinghouse Contracts, 1892-1901, ais 63:24, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Business and Industry; Business records; Manufacturing industries -- Capital investments -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Contracts -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Industrial procurement -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Westinghouse Electric & Manufacturing Company -- Records and correspondence
- Acme Machinery Co., December 19, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Alberene Stone Co., August 9, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Alberene Stone Co., January 3, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- American Gas Furnace Co., May 1901 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- American Tool Machine Co., April 20, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- American Watch Tool Co., April 3, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., December 19, 1892-April 17, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., March 25, 1893-April 19, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., February 1, 1894-December 18, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., February 21, 1894-July 27, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., February 12, 1894-October 8, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- U Baird Machinery Co., February 10, 1894-December 18, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., April 2, 1895-May 15, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., June 12, 1895-December 10, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., March 13, 1896-January 15, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., May 19 1898-June 15, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., June 15, 1898-June 22, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., October 4, 1898-November 1, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., December 6, 1898-December 23,1898 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., January 5, 1899-January 30, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., March 8, 1899-May 5, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., May 24, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., June 13, 1899-October 6, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., May 6, 1899-December 14, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., February 24, 1900-April 26, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., August 9, 1900-September 6, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., June 13, 1900-June 15, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., May 11, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., September 24, 1900-January 11, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., January 29, 1901-March 23, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., May 11, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., July 24, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
- U. Baird Machinery Co., August 2, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Barnes Safe Lock Co., July 2, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- E. Bartlett, June 13, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- John Becker, May 9, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Bement, Miles Co., April 30, 1894-June 8, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Bement, Miles Co., June 15, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Bement, Miles Co., September 1, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Bement, Miles Co., January 3, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Blake Johnson, January 23, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- E.W. Bliss Co., January 24, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- E.W. Bliss Co., December 12, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- E.W. Bliss Co., May 1, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Boomer Boschert Press Co., February 9, 1894-February 22, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Boomer Boschert Press Co., March 15, 1895 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Boomer Boschert Press Co., January 25, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Boomer Boschert Press Co., June 23, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Booth McQuaide, June 5, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Brown Sharpe, November 29, 1893-February 9, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Brown Sharpe, October 31, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Brown Zortman Machinery Co., June 15, 1900-October 19, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Brown Zortman Machinery Co., March 23, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Brown Zortman Machinery Co., May 10, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Brush Stephens, January 21, 1893-January 24, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Victor Buetner, November 20, 1896 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
- Bullard Machine Tool Co., June 10, 1898 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Central District Printing Telephone Co., November 28, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Challenge Machine Co., May 9, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Chicago Flexible Shaft Co., February 14, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Chicago Flexible Shaft Co., February 21, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Child Acme Cutter Press Co., January 28, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Cleveland Electric Manufacturing Co., April 4, 1894-August 28, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Cleveland Punch Shear Works Co., April 3, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Connersville Blower Co., February 20, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- D'Amour Littledale Machine Co., May 18, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Deane Steam Pump Co., June 26, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Defiance Machine Co., April 11, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Detroit Safe Co., June 24, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- A.S. Deutsch Co., February 16, 1893 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Dixon Woods Co., May 12, 1894 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Gustave Ehrhardt Sons, February 23, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Electric Storage Battery Co., April 12, 1894 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Empire Engine Motor Co., June 18, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Empire Engine Motor Co., July 20, 1901 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Fairbanks Co., November 1892 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Fairbanks Co., March 20, 1895 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- J.A. Fay Egan Co., February 28, 1901 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Ferracute Machine Co., February 15, 1894 (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
- Fischer Foundry Machine Co., November 28, 1892 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Frank Machiney Co., February 26, 1901 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Garvin Machine Co., January 25, 1901 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- E.O. Grabo, February 6, 1899 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Hartford Machine Screw Co., May 19, 1899 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- James T. Halsey, October 18, 1892 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Heyl Patterson, November 2, 1895 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Heyl Patterson, May 11, 1901 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Heyl Patterson, June 21, 1901 (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
- Albert M. Hill, April 8, 1895 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- R. Hoe Co., February 14, 1894 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Howe Scale Co., March 30, 1893-November 15, 1894 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Howe Scale Co., October 23, 1894 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- C.W. Hunt Co., January 3, 1901 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Ingersoll Milling Machine Co., April 4, 1893 (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Ingersoll Sergeant Drill Co., February 17, 1896 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- H.W. Johns Manufacturing Co., February 27, 1894 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- H.W. John Manufacturing Co., August 29, 1898 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Johnston Co., February 26, 1901 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Jones Lamson Machine Co., December 5, 1892 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Kilbourne Jacobs Manufacturing Co., April 8, 1896 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Kelley Bros. Spielman, May 9, 1899 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Arthur Kirk Son, January 18, 1893 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- N.N. Kratzer Co., May 18, 1901 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- N.N. Kratzer Co., August 2, 1901 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Manning, Maxwell Moore, January 4, 1893 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Manning, Maxwell Moore, May 15, 1895 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Manning, Maxwell Moore, June 18, 1895 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Manning, Maxwell Moore, May 9, 1899 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Manning, Maxwell Moore, May 24, 1899 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Manning, Maxwell Moore, July 7, 1899 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Manning, Maxwell Moore, July 27, 1899-August 21, 1899 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Manning, Maxwell Moore, August 9, 1899 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Manning, Maxwell Moore, October 6, 1899 (Box 6, Folder 18-19)
- Manning, Maxwell Moore, December 14, 1899 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Manning, Maxwell Moore, December 29, 1899-September 1, 1900 (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Manning, Maxwell Moore, February 20, 1901 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Manning, Maxwell Moore, March 23, 1901-May 11, 1901 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Manning, Maxwell Moore, May 1, 1901 (Box 6, Folder 24)
- J.J. McCabe, December 10, 1895 (Box 6, Folder 25)
- J.J. McCabe, April 29, 1899 (Box 6, Folder 26)
- J.S. McCormick Co., October 21, 1895 (Box 6, Folder 27)
- McKnight Elder, April 10, 1895 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- E. Monthemont, April 30, 1896 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Morgan Engineering Co., December 16, 1895 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Morgan Engineering Co., June 6, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Morgan Engineering Co., September 11, 1900 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Morse, Williams Co., October 2, 1895 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Niagara Machine Tool Works, June 23, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Niagara Machine Tool Works, November 2, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Niagara Machine Tool Works, April 7, 1900 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Niagara Machine Tool Works, December 12, 1900 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Niles Tool Works Co., June 2, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Peck, Stow Wilcox Co., May 9, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Pittsburgh Manufacturing Co., November 18, 1892 (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Pratt Whitney Co., February 22, 1894 (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Pratt Whitney Co., January 2, 1895-May 20, 1895 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Pratt Whitney Co., June 21, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Pratt Whitney Co., July 14, 1898-September 24, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Pratt Whitney Co., February 28, 1899-March 3, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Pratt Whitney Co., August 17, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Pratt Whitney Co., September 6, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 20)
- Pratt Whitney Co., July 3, 1899-December 14, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 21)
- Pratt Whitney Co., December 13, 1899- April 24, 1900 (Box 7, Folder 22)
- Pratt Whitney Co., June 13, 1900 (Box 7, Folder 23)
- Pratt Whitney Co., January 3, 1901 (Box 7, Folder 24)
- Henry E. Pridmore, October 6, 1900-December 19, 1900 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Henry E. Pridmore, April 9, 1901 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Henry E. Pridmore, April 28, 1901-June 29, 1901 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Reeves Pulley Co., May 5, 1899 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Reeves Pulley Co., May 5, 1899 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Reeves Pulley Co., June 24, 1899 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Reeves Pulley Co., July 7, 1899 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- J.M. Robinson Co., January 12, 1901 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Wm. B. Scaife Sons, November 18, 1895 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- J.J. Seelar, June 20, 1901 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Wm. P. Seibert, November 14, 1892 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Wm. Sellers Co., December 29, 1893 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Wm. Sellers Co., January 10, 1897 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Wm. Sellers Co., May 24, 1899 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Wm. Sellers Co., August 2, 1901 (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Snow Steam Pump Works, May 15, 1895 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Snow Steam Pump Works, May 11, 1901 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- B.F. Sturtevant Co., May 7, 1901 (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Stromberg Carlson Telephone Mfg. Co., June 28, 1901 (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Samuel C. Tatum Co., May 1, 1901 (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Thomson Electric Welding Co., March 12, 1901 (Box 8, Folder 21)
- M.B. Tidey, March 8, 1899 (Box 8, Folder 22)
- Tinius Olsen Co., June 27, 1900 (Box 8, Folder 23)
- Toote, Burt Co., December 13, 1899 (Box 8, Folder 24)
- Uehling-Steinbart Co., April 26, 1900-June 13, 1900 (Box 8, Folder 25)
- Warner Swansey, October 28, 1899-November 6, 1899 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Warner Swansey, February 14, 1900 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Warner Swansey, November 21, 1900-January 14, 1901 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Warner Swansey, January 14, 1901 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Warner Swansey, May 11, 1901 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Wellman-Seaver Engineering Co., June 22, 1898-June 3, 1901 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Westinghouse, Church, Kerr Co., March 21, 1895 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Westinghouse Machine Co., June 23, 1894 (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Whiting Foundry Equipment Co., June 18, 1895-August 7, 1901 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Whiting Foundry Equipment Co., December 18, 1899 (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Whiting Foundry Equipment Co., July 23, 1901 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Whitney Manufacturing Co., May 24, 1899 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- James Whyte Co., March 28, 1895 (Box 9, Folder 13)
- James Whyte Co., August 21, 1895 (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Charles E. Wright Co., February 16, 1900 (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Charles E. Wright Co., October 6, 1900 (Box 9, Folder 16)
- Charles E. Wright Co., December 12, 1900 (Box 9, Folder 17)
- R.D. Wood Co., December 3, 1895 (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Woodwell Hardware Co., March 16, 1895 (Box 9, Folder 19)